Tracy Family Papers, 1766-1925
Connecticut Historical Society
Tracy Family Papers
1766-1925
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Tracy Family
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
Biographical Sketch
Frederick Augustus Tracy was born October 25, 1789 at Norwich, Connecticut. He married Eliza Ripley in 1813 and they settled in New York City where he was a merchant, broker and active businessman. Their children included Frederick (b. 1814) John Ripley (1820-1855), Charles Augustus (b. 1826) and Margaret Sophia (b. 1831). John Ripley Tracy married Charlotte Gray (b. 1818) and settled in Hartford, Connecticut where he was a merchant, shipping guns to Australia and Peru, among other activities. Their children, born in Hartford, were John Frederick (b. 1844), Samuel Gray (b. 1846), Newbold Le Roy (b. 1853), Charlotte Gray (b. 1848), Annie Hinchley (b. 1850) and Sophia Dennie (b. 1854). Newbold immigrated to Australia where he married Florence Elstampe and had children Frederick LeRoy (b. 1885) and Eric Gray (b. 1893). Samuel G. Tracy invested in a variety of businesses including pearl cultivation and lubricating oils.
Scope and Content
The collection had been partially but incompletely processed shortly after receipt. Some of that initial arrangement has been retained. The materials are arranged in roughly chronological order, with the eldest generation first followed by children in their birth order. The papers of John Ripley Tracy, 1844-1858) primarily relate to his business interests, including the New Jersey Zinc and Copper Company, the railroad, the lead trade, the gun trade, and investments in a shot manufactory in Britain based on the purchase of a patent from David Smith. Among the more significant documents are those related to the consignment of guns to Australia in 1853, with Edward Wadsworth serving as Tracy’s agent in Australia, and another venture to sell Colt pistols in Callao, Peru. The earliest of his letters announces the birth of his first son in 1844. In addition to correspondence, John’s papers include financial documents and legal records, including a copy of his will, and deeds. John’s wife Charlotte Gray Tracy is represented by correspondence, some with friends but the bulk with family, namely Sarah Jane Gray LeRoy, Margaret Sophia Tracy, and her son John F. Tracy. John F. Tracy’s papers include legal documents and correspondence, 1861-1925. Samuel G. Tracy is represented by correspondence, 1912-1913 including letters to his sister Sophie, and records related to his interest in pearl cultivation, including the incorporation records of the American Pearl Corporation, 1905. Financial and legal records and product formulae of the Lovell & Tracy Oil Co. of Hartford, document Samuel’s interest in a local business. Newbold and Charlotte are represented by correspondence, primarily from family members. Of note is a series of letters to Anne Tracy from Genevieve Cowles, written from Palestine in 1909. Documents related to related families are arranged alphabetically and include genealogical notes on those families as well as original documents from the 18th and early 19th centuries. Unidentified correspondence is arranged at the back of the collection, along with a unique group of cards with images of birds created by real feathers
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Tracy family.; Cowles, Genevieve.; Gray family.; Ledlie family.; Tracy, Charlotte Gray, b. 1818.; Tracy, Charlotte Gray, b. 1848.; Tracy, John Ripley, 1820-1855.; Tracy, Newbold, b. 1853.; Tracy, Samuel Gray, b. 1846.
Corporate Names
American Pearl Corporation.; Lovell & Tracy Oil Co. (Hartford, Conn.)
Subjects
Colt firearms.; Pearl oyster culture.
Contents:
- Papers
  - John R. Tracy correspondence, 1844-1854 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - John R. Tracy correspondence, 1844-1854 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - John R. Tracy correspondence, 1844-1854 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John R. Tracy correspondence, 1844-1854 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - John R. Tracy letters from Crosby & Co., Callao, Peru, 1854-1858 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - John R. Tracy legal papers, including his will, 1852-1855 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - John R. and Charlotte Tracy deeds, 1840-1855 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - John R. Tracy financial documents regarding the sale of guns in Australia, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - John R. Tracy bills and receipts, 1853-1854 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Charlotte G. Tracy correspondence, 1843-1868 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Charlotte G. Tracy letters from Sarah Jane LeRoy, 1841, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Charlotte G. Tracy letters from Sophia Tracy, 1855-1860 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Charlotte G. Tracy letters from son John F. Tracy, 1855-1857 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - John F. Tracy assorted papers, 1861-1925 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Samuel G. Tracy correspondence and agreement with Burma Shell Co., 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Samuel G. Tracy letters to sister Sophia, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Samuel G. Tracy documents regarding pearl cultivation, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - American Pearl Co. incorporation papers, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Samuel G. Tracy assorted papers, 1895-1915 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lovell & Tracy formulae and legal and financial papers, 1895-1902 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lovell & Tracy formulae and legal and financial papers, 1895-1902 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Newbold LeRoy Tracy correspondence and information form, 1884-1911 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Charlotte Gray Tracy letters from Edward Tracy, 1851-1860 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Charlotte Gray Tracy letters from Charles and Frederick Tracy, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Charlotte Gray Tracy correspondence and church pamphlets, 1886-1912 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Anne Tracy letters from Genevieve Cowles in Palestine, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Genealogical notes on the Gray family, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gray family papers, 1826-1875, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Ledlie family original documents and undated genealogical notes, 1766-1798 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Smith family original documents and undated genealogical notes, 1815, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Extracts from British probate records regarding the estate of John Smith, ca. 1876 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Genealogical notes on the Tracy family, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letter from Mary (?) to her mother, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Assorted documents, including unidentified correspondence and an epic poem, 1777-1843, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bird pictures made with real feathers, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)